[Music]
Heat. Heat.
Hello. Good evening. Good day everybody
and welcome to this special 60inute
episode of Askabit. We're trying to make
up for the episode that we lost over the
weekend. I hope everyone's doing great
wherever you are in the world whether
it's day or night or evening or morning
and let's see who is there with us on
the live chat before we begin. I can see
ace photon hit praapati geopolitical dub
from indor. Today guest user 262 Aush
Singh Mystic SK Hensy Penguin Bonjour
Daksh
uh City Slicker meet Mystery Davik
Shrian Sanat MN Hensy Penguin again
Sparti Uturi Namaste Geopolitical again
Swami Jan Orbit and Markets Deepika
Gorab Banskota Dave Suraj Ulas Bruce
Wayne from Gotham City Aditya Gaquad
Polar Bear Gorish KB chat DSP who says I
don't receive notifications for your
channel anymore. Yes, I'm aware of the
situation. That's all right. Uh yeah I
know well thank you for letting me know.
Uh Shividas Bachari Raghav Malotra
Manisha Maiti love Travel Guru Nutan
Roshan Somi Jen from Jaipur and
everybody else. Okay so what all do we
have? Let's take this question from
Aayush. First of all please take a look
at uh the Indo France deal on the jet
engine that's happened and explain in
detail. Mthil Modi is also there, Gorab
from Sydney, Chira Raj and so on. So now
what's this Indrance deal on the jet
engine? So we still don't have the
details the the the contours of the
deal. What exactly is the deal? uh the
defense minister Shri Raj Rajnat Singh
GI the Raksham Mantri had tweeted about
this a while ago that we're going to be
making jet engines in India and we're
going to looks like uh we're going to
tie up with Safhan which is the French
company which was earlier called Snikma
and it looks like from what one hears
that there's going to be complete
transfer of technology of the jet engine
all of it end to end and the
manufacturing will happen in India
that's what one hears but we still don't
have an official statement an official
uh statement with the full contours of
the deal. So we don't know for sure as
of yet. I'm not sure if it has been
approved at the highest level and it has
been given the go ahead uh from both
sides but it looks like we are very
close to this thing this deal. So uh
it's it's still a work in progress. Once
we have more information we can look
into that. But it looks like the deal
which is more or less almost finalized
but not quite finalized. It's about the
production of of a new series of series
of jet engines which is which is going
to be a collaboration between India and
France. From France we'll have snik
snikma yeah safh and from India we will
probably have DRDO probably uh and the
production will happen in India and the
co-development and so on and this will
be used for the upcoming fifth
generation fighter plane of India um and
possibly even the the possibly I'm not
sure I we'll have to look into that. So
uh we'll see about that.
Now next
geopolitical dub says how do you see
quad's future now? Well let's see how it
goes. You see uh there's supposed to be
a quad summit in India in the coming
weeks sometime in the coming couple of
months maybe September maybe this month
maybe October somewhere
on the horizon we have this upcoming
quad summit. The question is will this
summit go ahead? Will the great
president of the United States Shri
Donald Trump G will he come to India?
I think that is going to be a great
indicator of the future of Quad of the
Quad. I think the way the US is going
hammer and tongs after India and the
kind of statements that Trump's minions
like Pete Navaro and various other
minions are are making, it looks like
they the the attitude towards India is
very hostile right now. And if their
attitude towards India is super hostile,
I don't see really a viable future for
the Quad. And considering the events
that have happened in in China the past
couple of days, Mr. Modi meeting with
Mr. Xi and Mr. Putin and it looks like
there's been a reset of some kind
between India and China to some extent.
There's still major issues to to work
work through, but it looks like Mr. Modi
is signaling to the US that you know
what, we have options. we have
alternatives and if if this is the
attitude you're going to show then we
will not pick up your phone calls and we
and I'll go and talk with Mr. Putin and
Mr.
So I think the the future of the quad is
kind of shaky right now. It's on shaky
ground and depending on how the US
behaves the next few weeks the quad may
either continue in some shape or form or
it may dissolve and instead of a quad it
may become a trilateral between the US,
Australia and Japan which defeats the
purpose of the quad. Without India
there's no quad. So I think the future
is very 50/50 right now. Very shaky for
the quad.
MK says, "Was the early British
Parliament similar to the Roman Senate?
In both systems, power was distributed
among the elites?" No, it was very
different from the Senate. See, in the
Roman Senate, the full power lied lay
with the Senate. In Rome, when you had
the Senate during the Roman Republic
period, see Rome had three periods. The
Roman Kingdom, the Roman Republic, and
the Roman Empire. The Roman Empire
starts with uh Augustus.
Augustus, right? Uh Julius Caesar's uh
adoptive hair. So during the Roman
Republic period, the Senate had all the
power in Rome and there was no king or
emperor in Rome. All the power was
vested in the Senate. Those that bunch
of old guys wearing togas who would
discuss what happens and discuss the big
issues of the day and make decisions
which would be implemented. So the
Senate was all powerful in the British
Parliament. The British Parliament was
kind of a compromise between the king
and the nobles,
right? Between the crown and the nobles.
So in the UK, you still had the
supremacy, the majesty of the crown and
some power lay with parliament. So it
was kind of a compromise, right? But the
majority of the power still lay with the
crown. The crown could do things that
the parliament could not and the
parliament could not veto the crown
mostly. Some things say it would be it
would be they would allow it to slide.
But over time the parliament became
became more and more powerful. Today it
is said that the UK crown is a
figurehead but uh 100 years ago it was
different. 200 years ago it was very
different. So over time the British
parliament became more and more
powerful. But historically if you see
for the majority of the time the
parliament existed in the UK in Britain
it was nowhere as powerful as uh the
Senate in Rome.
Genuine beatboxes Rafal fighter jets we
bought those also not 100% technology
transfer yeah well you see transfer of
technology is very expensive no nation
is willing to give up its technology
just for a couple of billion dollars
maybe $10 billion or whatever it is
you've got to pay see technology is is
developed over decades
and the price and if you have spent
decades like 40 50 60 years developing a
a certain piece of technology
You're going to put a very heavy price
on that. It's not like you're going to
the market buying tomatoes and potatoes.
This is a whole different thing. And we
bought how many? 24 26 Rafals. If we had
given an order for 200 Rafal, well, they
would have shifted the whole production
line to India and probably given the
whole technology transfer to India. If
you buy a small number of Rafal jets,
well, then it doesn't work. And uh so
that's how it goes. You are right that
when we bought the Rafal jets we did not
get the full transfer of technology and
when it comes to the Rafal you see it's
not just one it's not one potato it's
got so many different components that
are made manufactured by different
companies and you got to deal with each
of these companies individually you can
of course do it through the French
government in case the price is high
enough because see when it comes to the
Rafael the the jet engines are are
manufactured by Safhan the ejection she
seat is probably manufactured by Baker
and whatever it is the the UK company
and so much more. So it's anyway it's
impossible to get a full technology
transfer but the main piece that we are
looking for is the jet engine. So that's
that's what the talk is about these
days.
Shankar Mahadevan says that Jake
Sullivan has said that Trump's business
is the reason behind the attack on us
Jacob Bababad air base where we hit
where we hit during operation sindur.
Jake Sullivan, have you watched my geost
strategy episodes which I have
discontinued because of the shadow ban
on my channel?
I have gone into excruciating detail
about the kind of business deals Trump
has in Pakistan.
He is very heavily personally invested
in Pakistan.
Okay, that's the deal. That's why he is
so pro Pakistan. That's why the US
regime, the Trump regime is so pro
Pakistan. And this is going to continue.
and he has been allowed to do this
because he has kissed the ring and the
deep state has approved this. So yeah,
Trump is personally invested in
Pakistan. He wants to extract $50
trillion worth of uh oil and gas and row
materials from Pakistan. The Pakistanis
are willing to sell off their country to
Trump as long as they support as long as
the US supports Pakistan. So yeah,
MK says is history repeating itself?
Europe going through Yamna 2.0 and
Constantinization 2.0 ongoing genetic
and religious re-engineering through
demographic imig through through illegal
immigration.
You see, if
if Brussels is engineering the
immigration, it's no longer really
illegal.
The the Parliament of the UK
Excuse
me.
Okay, let's take this question again. Is
one second. Let me see. So, everyone is
saying that the video is blurred. Is it?
Is the video blurred?
Just please let me know on the live chat
if the video is blurry, sound is
lagging, everything is lagging.
Wonderful, wonderful, wonderful. Give me
a second. I'll have to fix this.
Okay, looks like something is blurred.
Give me a second, please.
All right. I apologize for that problem.
I hope that we are we are better now. Uh
please do let me know if uh
if
ah it's fine now. Yeah, I think it's
fine now. Well, thank you for letting
know letting me know. So coming back to
the question is history repeating
itself? Is Europe going through Yamna
2.0 and Constantinization 2.0 ongoing
genetic and religious re-engineering
through illegal immigration? First of
all, the immigration that's happening in
Europe is not illegal. It is being uh it
is being mandated by Brussels. See,
Europe is ruled from Brussels. Brussels
is the uh seat of power of the European
Union. And the government, I mean the
the the bureaucrats who rule Europe from
Brussels. They have mandated that every
EU country should bring in a certain
number of immigrants from specific
countries every year. Every nation has a
kota of immigrants or refugees or
whatever they have to allow in their
country every year. Well, if that's the
case, it's no longer illegal. It is
legal. It is being mandated from from
the top from the rulers of Europe who
are not democratically elected. So uh we
are seeing we definitely seeing genetic
demographic religious re-engineering of
of Europe through forcible
uh through through the countries being
forced to accept immigrants. That is
what's going on. And yeah, you could say
well it's not Yamna 2.0 because Yamna
was an invasion that was done by horses
by horsemen. It was an invasion
through the borders of whatever you know
communities existed at the time. This is
different. This is being done
bureaucratically. So it's not that sort
of invasion. It's a bureaucratically
uh engineered uh invasion.
Constantinization 2.0. Yeah. Constantin
Constantinization. By that you refer to
the forcible Christianization of Europe
which was done through force through
through brutality. Well once again maybe
a new religion is being brought into
Europe and it's not probably being done
through force. It's just being done
through migration. So it's a different
way of doing the same thing of achieving
the same objective in Europe.
Proud Dana says, "Navaro's comments
about brahinss make me think this
Harvard DNA lab is CIA etc. program as
well." So yeah, this this individual,
Trump's minion, Navaro, Pete Navaro, the
guy who was in jail this time last year.
This time last year, the guy was in
jail. He's a convicted felon. That's the
kind of individual that Trump has
brought to, you know, elevated to his
minionship.
Uh so Navaro went he has been going he
has been ranting against India multiple
times on on American national television
and the most recent rant is about
brahinss. He's saying that the brahinss
in India are are profiting from Russian
oil from Putin's oil and that's how
that's how the brahinss are
marginalizing and oppressing the rest of
Indians and they are profiting from
Putin's oil and and funding Putin's war
in Ukraine. Essentially, that's what he
is saying. He's trying to create some
kind of he's kind trying to engineer
some kind of cast divide in India,
right? And Indians have this massive
inferiority complex. When a white man
says something, they will start dancing
on the top of the roofs that yes, white
man said this, so it must be true. And
Navaro is not even really a white man.
He's a he's a Latino. Anyhow, he's white
enough for Indians, isn't he? Uh, so the
Americans have been playing this game
for quite for a very long time. For
decades they have been trying to create
and and and widen various kinds of
divisions in India, fissures in India,
through various NOS's through through uh
university professors and so on. The
entire academic system has been hijacked
by the leftists in India and Indian
leftists are not like Chinese leftists,
communists who are highly patriotic.
Indian leftists are mercenaries. they
will work for the highest power for the
highest bidder right they will they
essentially will I'm not naming anybody
by the way okay I'm not naming anybody
I'm sure there are good leftists also
but uh it is it it it's apparent it's
clear that many Indian leftists are are
up for hire and they have been working
if you look at the if you look at
various Indian academic departments
humanities departments I'm sure some are
great but many of them they will write
the only research that comes out of
these these departments the research
papers is all about cast cast. So
they're trying to create this this huge
narrative for decades that India is
ridden by cast wars and all that and
they're trying to actually make the
students believe it and and generations
of students have grown up believing all
this nonsense. So the Americans have
created this the all the the groundwork
for what Navaro is now trying to achieve
by of of creating divisions in India and
maybe weaponizing those those divisions.
So all of this is how DNA labs hard
Harvard CIA all of yeah it's all it's
all interconnected and that's what
they're trying to do the end objective
is to balkcanize India it's to fragment
and fracture India so that so that India
can never achieve its potential that's
the objective the Americans are pretty
overt now in what they're trying to do
the objective is no longer possibly to
contain India it's to fragment India
bulcanize India
says how India's capture of Kailasha
heights during conflict in 2020 forced
per to come to negotiating table.
Well, I haven't looked into the tactical
events of what happened in 2020. I I
look at a at a at a at a different see
when it comes to a conflict. You there
are different ways of looking at it.
Different lenses. You can look at from a
very microscopic perspective. What
happened those 20 m this these 2
kilometers? What happened? This this
mountain peak or this hilltop who
captured this the finger one finger two
finger three of Pangong Lake. What is
happening there? the those 300 mters
who's there 200 m here what's there
that's one way of looking at it that's
how the army looks at it the army looks
at it from a tactical perspective and
also from a strategic perspective but
this is a tactical perspective the way
the way I look at conflicts is from a
different perspective from through a
different lens I look at objectives I
look at agendas I look at what is this
guy's national interest what is this
guy's national interest what does each
party want the higher ground who has the
advantage what is the long-term
objective all of that So I don't know
what exactly happened Kailasha heights
this hilltop we captured and what
happened but yeah see the basic
principle in in any in in the in the
military domain is that whoever has the
higher ground has has the advantage.
Okay. So if you have a higher ground and
you're going to fight with someone then
your opponent will have to come and
fight you. You he have to come upwards
and spend more energy while you can
conserve energy and and shoot down shoot
downwards.
So uh so obviously that will give you an
advantage and there is the deal.
Okay, next question.
Karthika says, "You said a military coup
will never happen. Not last, I said it
will never happen. It won't ever succeed
in India." That's what I said. What are
the reasons for it? Is there a
possibility of a regime change in India
by foreign powers?
Okay. So uh now if you ask me what are
the reasons why regime change why why a
coup can never happen in India. See
there are I don't remember the exact
specific details of the three conditions
that Edward Lutat put forth in his book.
One is is that see one of the conditions
there are three conditions that need to
be satisi that need to be present in a
country for a coup to ever succeed. If
those three conditions aren't present in
the country then a coup can never
succeed. Firstly, the country should be
dominated by a single ethnic group and a
single linguistic group. For example,
China. The entire country is dominated
by the Hanchinese in this one primary
language which dominates the whole
thing. There are many other so-called
ethnic groups in China, not so-called
actual ethnic groups, but those are
marginalized and small in number.
Right? So, there's only one ethnic group
in China, the Hanchinese. And there's
only one linguistic group in China more
or less. So that is the first condition.
In India you have
you have so many different India is so
diverse. We are one ethnicity Indians
but we look up if you look at how
Indians see themselves. The truth is
that Indians prioritize their
subnational identity more than the
national identity. I am Bengali. I am
Asamese. I am Tamil. I am Punjabi. I'm
Oranavi. I'm Maharashtrian. I'm
Gujarati. I am Andra. I'm I'm whatever.
Indians always prioritize their
subnational identity over their national
identity. Always there are very few of
them who actually truly inside their
heart believe we are Indians first. And
many people will say will in public say
no no no it is not like that. But the
truth we all know.
So we prioritize our regional and
linguistic identity over our national
identity. In a country like that a coup
can never succeed. Secondly, the second
condition is that for a a coup to
succeed in a country, there needs to be
a huge divide between the elites and the
downtrodden
huge divide in ter in terms of means. So
the elites must be living in walled
gardens with all the privilege in the
world and the common people must be
living in abject poverty. That's what
you see typically in African nations.
That's very what you see in nations
where there is a lot of inequality.
So the elites have all the power and the
the common people have no power. They're
completely helpless and they are
typically extremely poor. Well, India is
indeed a poor country for sure. If you
look at GDP per capita, yeah, that is
true. But if you look at the genie
coefficient, the inequality index, India
is the world's fourth least inequal.
It's not number one in the least inequal
countries but it's number four in the
least inequal countries unequal
countries inequality. So India is one of
the most egalitarian countries in the
world and that's why once again a regime
change operation can a coup can never
succeed in India. And the third thing I
don't remember it right now but you can
look up the book by Edward Lutwak. So
there are reasons which need there are
very specific conditions that need to be
satisfied for a coup to ever succeed in
a country and India is not one of those
countries. Regime change operation is a
whole different thing that can actually
happen if the groundwork is laid over
many years and probably it is being laid
by for many years by the United States
in India to conduct a regime change
operation in India. Maybe they they will
try and attempt this in the next year or
two. It's possible the Americans.
Okay. Amisha says can we trust China? It
can be a neu moment for Modi. You cannot
trust China. You cannot trust anybody.
But you can trust them to prioritize
their own national interests. And if you
know what their national interest is,
you know what they want. Now we have to
understand that Nehu Gi and Modi G are
different people. Mr. Modi G is not Shri
Neuji. Okay. Modi G is not Nehuji. So
that is well you see nobody can be as
magnificent as Shri Nuji. Right? So Modi
G is not Neuji. So I think we can rest
assured that we are in good hands. But
yeah, China, we can work with China. But
you always have to keep double-checking
everything. That that essentially
applies to everybody every other
country. In the past, our foreign policy
was extremely naive and that is why we
we faced the situations that we faced
with China. Right. Okay.
Next. Mahar KVS says Indian immigrants
are contributing more to the western
economies compared to Chinese
immigrants. Is it a question? It's a
question. But westerners love Chinese
more than Indians. Is there a black pill
element to this or soft power issue?
There's nothing to do with soft power.
The reason why the west hates India
right now is that India is daring to
stand up and try and become a great
power. India is right now the fourth
largest economy. No, it cannot it can no
longer be ignored. India is soon going
to leapfrog the number four three
economy and become the third largest
economy. We have gone ahead of the UK,
going ahead of Germany. We will soon go
ahead of Japan. We'll be number three.
All the other white countries, European
countries will be behind us. That
infuriates these people. That infuriates
the West. How dare you brown folks who
we had almost destroyed. How dare you
not die? How did you manage to survive?
How dare you stand up again? Right? They
don't care what you contribute to their
economy.
Now why this this uh approach towards
Indians as opposed to the Chinese?
Because they ruled India. They didn't
rule China. They ruled India. And every
country they ruled has been destroyed
thoroughly culturally, economically,
civilizationally, in every way. The
every country has been bulcanized. Look
at Africa. Look at the map of Africa.
You have straight lines across Africa.
The original shapes of the of the of the
empires and kingdoms have been wiped
out. No one even remembers them. That is
what they've done. They've reshaped
Africa in their own image. They've done
the same to the Middle East. Look at the
straight lines in the maps in the Middle
East. When it comes to India, we have to
some we also have balconized. They want
to balconize us further. But we have not
allowed them to totally destroy us. So
they hate that. The Chinese, they could
not rule China. They they did not have
the time to rule China by the time the
age of colonization was coming to an
end. The day age of direct colonization,
right?
So they don't see the see the Chinese
the same way. They see the Chinese as as
a country as a civilization that they
have never really defeated. So then they
they are fine with that. But India was a
defeated civilization. And how dare
India rise again. That's the hatred.
Okay. The westerners have no love for
China. But they tolerate the Chinese
more than the Indians. They just hate
the Indians because they consider
Indians first of all as brownskinned
people to be inferior and secondly a
defeated civilization. How dare you rise
again? And how dare you be proud of
India? How dare you? only we folks have
the right to be proud of ourselves. That
sort of thing. It's it's a very deep
visceral deep-seated hatred. It's very
deep in the deep inside.
MK says India and Pakistan have similar
cultural backgrounds. Absolutely not.
What what similar cultural backgrounds?
Where where sir
where do we have similar cultural
backgrounds? We have the same genetics.
Yeah. And yeah little bit of uh little
bit of tradition still continue in some
in some shape or form. The Pakistanis
also I think I I believe that they
respect respect their elders the way we
do. I think they they conduct mar
marriage ceremonies in some ways
reminiscent of the old ways despite the
Islamic angle because in Pakistan also
some I suppose the brides wear bright
red colors and all that if I'm not
mistaken I may be wrong in that also I
don't know. So many of the old
traditions have somehow survived. But
culturally,
culturally Pakistan has nothing to do
with us anymore.
Culturally they are not similar to us.
Background, genetic background, history,
heritage 10,000 years ago, same. Sure.
Culturally completely different from
India. Look at how Indians behave in the
UK and look at how Pakistanis behave in
the UK. Do you see the cultural
difference?
What are Pakistanis famous for in the
UK?
Do I have to do I have to use those
words? Those words should not be uttered
in a in in in
any civilized
discussion. Right? Uh so the point is
I'm just seeing the chat. Do we have any
issues? No, we don't. Right. Hopefully.
Right.
Oh, okay. People are reminding me it's
not India and Pakistan, it's Iran and
Pakistan.
Okay, the video quality is again blurry
apparently.
Well, that's lovely.
That's lovely. I apologize. I thought I
had fixed the thing.
Give me a second, please.
Oh, hello. Testing.
>> One second. One second.
Okay.
Come.
This one.
Um,
okay. I think we are fine now. Uh, let
me just double check with the with the
audience with the live chat. Am I
audible now? Am I visible? Yeah, I
apologize for the delay. Ah, I don't
know. Yeah, I think we're fine now.
Okay, I apologize once again. Let me go
back to what I was talking about. I
remember people reminding me I it's Iran
not Pakistan.
Okay. So Iran and Pakistan have similar
cultural backgrounds. Yet you say
Pakistan could not develop its own nukes
because of its own culture. Why is that?
Oh well interesting question that you
ask. Well has Iran developed its own
nukes?
Has it? Well if you have two countries
which have similar cultures and similar
backgrounds and one has developed nukes,
one hasn't developed nukes, then we can
compare. Well, which country has
developed nukes? Secondly, Pakistan.
Yeah, culturally, culturally they are
still not the same. They are both
countries that have been converted to a
foreign religion. True. Iran for almost
1,200,300 years. Pakistan for the past,
I don't know 500 or so years, maybe
slightly longer than that depending on
how we see it. But the thing is Pakistan
is a colonized state. It's it's a it's a
mercenary state. It's a nation that is
uh has been created artificially by a
foreign country and the only purpose of
the existence of Pakistan is to serve
foreign objectives, right?
And you don't allow a nation like that
to be able to develop nuclear weapons.
You don't allow that. You give them
nuclear weapons. You allow them to keep
them, but you don't allow them to
develop the knowhow, the technology, all
of that on their own. Look at their
abysmal system, their education system.
I mean, I talk about India's education
system, which is terrible. I mean look
at Pakistan's education system. Look at
their physics syllabus. Look at the
textbooks that they have physics
textbooks. Have you seen I I I I have
the misfortune of of seeing somewhere
online the first few pages of a
Pakistani physics textbook. If you read
what's written there then you would
understand that they can't develop the
nuclear their own nuclear weapons. So
it's it's more to do not about I I have
never said Pakistan first of all I have
never said Pakistan could not develop
its own nukes because of culture. I
never said that.
So let's not put words in someone's
mouth. Okay. Pakistan is a is is is an
abysmally underdeveloped country. It's a
vasalized country. It's a mercenary
country. It's a country that is run by a
small group of dictators. It is highly
unfortunate the situation Pakistan is
in. It is terrible for the people of
Pakistan. It has nothing to do with
Pakistan culture.
All right.
Our friend James has returned. Cheerio
James, how are you doing, sir? How are
you doing? It's always good to see you,
James. It's always good to see you.
James, our friend, our former colonial
overlord, says that London thrives
eternal. Your cities decay still. Well,
I remember the last time I was in
London. There was garbage thrown all
over the streets. I saw some bobbies,
some cops eating a packet of chips and
just dumping the packet of chips on the
street. I saw people smoking cigarettes
and stuff snuffing the butts out on the
pavement. And I saw the situation in
London and other parts of England.
You're talking about decay. Well,
please, Sir James, please take a look at
your cities and see, please take a look
at what's being done to your cities and
your people and your children by
Pakistanis, by Pakistanis.
Pakistanis
and just and then compare it with India.
I mean you people destroyed India
abysmally. When you people left our uh
our life expectancy was 31. Imagine what
you did to my people. Our life
expectancy was 31. And see where we are
today. We we were we were beggared by
you. Utterly beggared. There was nothing
left. Our GDP was 33% of the world's GDP
when you came in. And by the time you
left it was less than 2% of the world's
GDP. It's going to take us some time to
get back on our feet. But now we are
getting back on our feet. And that's why
you people are so upset. So upset. Dear
James, take care of your country, man.
Do that. Take care of your women folk.
Do something about the Pakistanis. Well,
I think it's too late for that. It's too
late for that, James. I really,
you know, some part of me feels sorry
for your people. It's not their fault. I
mean, look, you guys genocided us. You
did. you did whatever you did to us.
It's not the fault of today's English
English men and English women. So I I
kind of feel sorry for them. But maybe
it's karma. Maybe you do pay the price
for the sins of your ancestors.
All right, James. Cheerio.
Ashtohi says, "What does common Russian
people gain from India India Russia
relations and vice versa? Apart from
energy, defense, security, how can
common Indians profit from Russian
market?" Well, if you manufacture things
in India, if India becomes a
manufacturing power, let's say you
manufacture all kind of things, watches,
shoes, guns, helicopters, cars,
I don't know, whatever.
Sell it to Russia, you'll make money.
I'm sure the Russian uh market will be
happy to, you know, buy Indian products.
So, both nations benefit, both nations
benefit, both sets of people benefit.
uh if India doesn't become a
manufacturing power then we will simply
have government-to-government relations
then there's going to be less
people-to-people connection but if India
does become a major manufacturing power
then we will have lots of trade
relations which bring in
people-to-people relations how did the
whole of Southeast Asia become
Indianized it started through trade
didn't it that's how it started trade is
is is a great catalyst trade can start
kickstart a lot and then we can open up
um you know I mean I've been saying this
for such a such a long time India has
the potential to become a tourism
superpower then you can have Russians
coming in coming here and Indians can
visit Russia right Russia also has so
many tourist destinations so there's a
lot that can be done if we get things
right yeah so how can a common Indian
profit from the Russian market well
become a manufacturer manufacture
something export it to the Russian
market get a profit that's how it goes
Uh hush says you have mentioned India as
one of the least inequal countries but I
see every time opposition targeting
billionaires in mentioning inequality.
You see you have to create fake
narratives right I mean I don't know I I
have not seen the opposition who is
doing what and all that. Okay, I look at
the geopolitics globally, but
hypothetically if you were in the
opposition, okay, and and hypothetically
if you were some hypothetical political
party with hypothetical connections to a
superpower and the superpower wants to
destabilize India and and and effect put
create the groundwork for a future
regime change operation, then you create
fake narratives in India through a
hypothetical connection with a
hypothetical political party. H that's
how you do it. So what do you do? You
target the most successful people. Who
are the most successful people? The
people who have become billionaires by
succeeding and many of these billion I
mean is is is being a billionaire a bad
thing? It means you did something right.
If you did it in a rotten system maybe
you did you took some shortcuts perhaps.
I don't know. I'm just saying
hypothetically.
The thing is India needs more
billionaires. I would like a 100,000
billionaires in in India. I want all of
you to become billionaires. What's wrong
with that?
So by targeting billionaires, what
you're saying is that being successful
is bad. Remain poor. We will worship the
poor. We will worship poverty and we
hate success.
So
you know that's what I can say about I
will not go further into this because
this is about domestic politics and I
don't really talk about that.
Godliness says listening to many retired
diplomats, army officers and especially
some high some right-wing commentators.
Uh it seems like the
it seems like the love Indian political
thought and human resources have for the
west is everlasting. Um let's say it's
possible. Yeah, I I I note what you're
saying,
right?
Is it surprising? Maybe it's not that
surprising. I'm sure not all retired
diplomats do this. I'm sure not all
retired army officers do this. I'm sure
not all right-wing commentators do this.
But it is possible that many of them do
it. It may perhaps be possible.
See, geopolitical commentary has become
an industry in India. Now in 2020, it
was just a small number of people. But
now you have heavyweights in the Indian
geopolitical commentary industry. There
are two classes of these heavyweights in
Indian geopolitical commentary today.
There are three classes actually. One is
journalists who have rebranded
themselves as geopolitical commentators.
They are typically new news readers.
They used to read news from a
teleprompter. Now they are regarded as
geopolitical analysts because they kept
on reading the same international news,
foreign policy news. So they they are
now regarded as geopolitical
commentators. That's number one. Number
two is retired diplomats.
Okay. And number three is retired army
officers. So there are three classes of
Indian geopolitical commentators. And
look, you don't make money doing
geopolitical commentary, right? You make
money by being part of some organization
somewhere. Maybe a think hypothetically
some think tank or hypothetically some
other organization which may have
funding from somewhere hypothetically
perhaps. I am not naming anybody by the
way. So don't don't please don't you
know attempt to create some controversy.
I'm naming nobody. I'm saying
hypotheticals.
There could be see there are so many
think tanks in the world and so many of
these think tanks hypothetically could
have funding from hypothetical
superpowers or whatever. So if if you
are hypothetically in one of these think
tanks or associate or maybe you want to
become in a part of a hypothetical think
tank then you may uh have the tendency
to have a love affair with the west. So
I think that should explain things and
if you are hypothetically uh political I
mean I mean I mean a journalist in so
and so media outlet hypothetical media
outlet and if that media outlet has
funding from wherever then you're going
to sing those tunes.
So today geopolitical commentary in
India has become noise. Absolute noise.
99.9% of it is absolute garbage. Truly
there superficial stuff surface level
stuff and most of it is it looks like
it's paid commentary.
Not all.
Uh Pratt Dana says James sent rupees. L
James seems to be on a trip visit to
India perhaps.
MK says, "Many one man show empires
ended after them like Napoleon, Hitler.
Will it be the case with Putin? Why
doesn't Great Britain Empire vaselize
neighbors like as any other empire
does?" Interesting questions. You're
right. Many such empires ended after the
big guy passed on or or gave gave up
power.
See, like I've always said, I've been
saying this for years, the critical time
period in any empire's history, the most
vulnerable time period is the time of
the handover. Have you seen a relay
race, 100 m relay, you hold a baton and
you run 100 m and by the time you're
reaching the 100 meter mark, your your
your colleague is there who starts
sprinting and you to hand the baiton to
the colleague. Now while handing over
the bait and if the baiton falls down
you're disqualified it's done finished.
Similarly in an empire when you have a
great emperor and the empire is great
the critical most vulner vulnerable
moment is the time of handover to the
next to the successor. If the succession
goes wrong, if the successor is weak, if
the su successor is unqualified, if the
successor is inept, incompetent, then
everything your predecessor did is going
to be waste, wasted away, frittered
away, right? The succession is the most
important thing. So yeah, Napoleon,
Hitler was defeated. Hitler was
defeated. He he made too many blunders.
Napoleon again himself was defeated. But
somehow kind of his legacy continued for
a while. Putin. So it will depend on who
Mr. Putin appoints as his successor.
Right now I don't see anybody on the
horizon and maybe it's a good thing for
Mr. Putin that he has not made it open
overt keep it very secret but eventually
Mr. Putin will have to hand it over to
somebody one way or the other right the
ideal situation is that he decides when
he step steps down and who who is the
successor and he retains some power for
some time to ensure things go well. So
if that goes fine then the empire won't
won't be destroyed then it will last it
may thrive it may even do better so it
all depends on who comes next does Mr.
Putin decide or is it all left to chance
which is stupid.
Why doesn't why didn't didn't Great
Britain Empire vaselize neighbors like
any empire does? The Great Britain
Empire vaselize the whole world. So
Dark Knight says is the accepted
narrative of AQ Khan stealing nuclear
tech fake since you claim PAC doesn't
have its own nukes and the reports of
Pakistan providing nuclear technology to
North Korea are also fake. We have been
sold all these stories and we have
swallowed them wholesale. Uh what we
know see what we have been told is that
Pakistan developed a nuclear bomb. How
did they develop it? Because Abdul Kadir
Khan this great Pakistani physicist he
stole some blueprints and he brought
them to Pakistan and through the
blueprints they developed nuclear
weapons. Are you people kidding me? He
stole a bunch of blueprints. Is your is
your security so lax that a Pakistani
nuclear scientist can steal blueprints
from Netherlands or wherever? Yeah.
Really? And based on the blueprints, he
made nuclear weapons. Are you people
kidding me? What are we 3 years old? Do
you believe this is a Mickey Mouse
story? Yeah. This is a nice cover story
they've made up.
Pakistan providing nuclear technology to
North Korea. I think it was the the
Chinese who may have helped North Korea
with something or the other. Right. And
the story is that the the the Chinese
then passed on new North Korean rocket
or missile designs to Pakistan. I am not
sure what exactly is the situation
between North Korea and Pakistan. But I
don't believe for one instance for one
moment that Pakistan developed its own
nuclear technology. Nothing to do with
culture. Nothing to do with culture.
More to do with their education system
and the abysmal quality of the
technology technicians, engineers and
scientists. Nah.
So I believe this entire story is a nice
cover story that gullible people have
swallowed hook line and sinker. I don't
believe it.
Virgo's sager says Navaro meant Boston
Brahman's Indian equivalent. That's what
some Indians are trying to now say to
cover up what Navaro has said. No no no
no no. In the US they had this term
called Boston Brahmans.
You see when uh when Plymouth was
founded and the and the pilgrims stepped
on the rock of Plymouth and established
the first settlement which was not the
first settlement. The first was
Jamestown by the way but when they
established Plymouth they eventually in
a few years established Boston in the
Boston Harbor and those were the first
immigrants from England to the US and
they are the Boston Brahmans the
highclass people. That's what they say.
There was a term called Boston Brahmans.
still exists by the way the people who
are called Boston Brahmans they still
have English accent accents British
accents but Navaro did not mean that
okay if some if some individuals on
Indian Twitter are claiming that then I
would like to look at who is funding
them that's all I'll say
bonjour I joined late says anonymous
scientist the why does the US want to
start a conflict with Venezuela what are
the planning look Venezuela is rich in
oil Venezuela is run by Maduro who is
anti-US
who refuses to cave in and become a US
wasal and do everything US says and sell
oil as per US directives and that's why
the US is unhappy with that and maybe
they will do a coup there maybe they
will just invade like they invaded
Nicaragua perhaps yeah so the deal is
that Venezuela refuses to be a US wasal
if you look at the entirety of Latin
America all the countries in Latin
America they are all US the polite term
is allies is so Venezuela refuses to be
a US ally just like Cuba. So that's why
they are uh singled out for special
treatment. You see
um Sarram says China grew at 14% per
year at their peak
uh India can't reach 8%. Why? Simple
difference very simple. China is a
dictatorship. India is a chaotic
democracy. If you have a dictatorship
the same kind of dictatorship you have
in China if you have the same thing in
India India will also grow at 14% per
year. If you have someone like Emperor
Ashok at the helm who you can't mess
with okay you don't mess with Emperor
Ashoke. If you have somebody like that
at the helm that's sort of dictatorship
India India may even surpass what China
did but we are a democracy democracies
are so we can't grow like that. We
should be happy with 6 and a half 7%.
Yeah. Pratt Dhana says coverage of Iran
Israel war by our right-wing people
opened my eyes and now they are clear
cleaning Trump's mess by calling it ego
battle between Modi and Trump but it's
not it is not an ego battle with between
Mr. Modi and Trump. There are many
people I don't know about right-wing,
leftwing, that's a different story.
Okay, I'll not go into that direction.
But many Indians are saying and many
Americans are also saying that Modi is
being Modi is being stubborn. Modi is
being obsinate. We know Trump is a very
childish person. He's a very egoistic
person. Just massage Trump's ego. Just
nominate him for a Nobel Prize. Just say
that yes, Trump, you played a role in
the ceasefire with Pakistan and
everything is fine. Is that going to
solve the problems? You see what does
Trump really want?
The Nobel Prize thing and the Pakistan
operation sindur thing it is a cover
story. What Trump really wants is that
India should open up its entire market
to the American exports. India should
apply 0% tariffs on American imports.
India should open up its agricultural
sector to American imports. So we should
allow American agricultural imports and
dairy imports into India with 0%
tariffs. What will that do? Right now
people are claiming in India that the
Trump tariffs are hurting India's
economies and they are putting
businesses putting you know companies
out of business and people are losing
the jobs. If you do what Trump says our
entire manufacturing sector and
agricultural sector will be out of
business. H then what happens? It's
nothing to do with ego. It's nothing to
do with the Nobel Prize or the or or
accepting uh to have to to massage
Trump's ego that he uh did the
ceasefire. It's nothing to do with that.
That is not going to solve the problem.
If that was all it took, we would have
done it. But Trump's Trump wants more.
He doesn't want a pound of flesh. He
wants a ton of flesh. And the people who
are, you know, claiming that India
should just massage Trump's ego and
that's all it takes. Well, either they
are naive or or or sir there is
something else behind it. Iran Israel
war I mean lots of Indian so-called
right yeah rightwingers also they're
like yes hammer Iran what how naive can
people be Iran is on our side Iran is
not an adversary the last time you had a
pro- US puppet regime in Iran they were
pro Pakistan
today's Iran government is not pro
Pakistan they are anti-Pakistan they
don't like Pakistan they hate Pakistan
they even bombed Pakistan a couple of
years ago The moment you have a regime
change in Iran and this government falls
and you have a pro-Israel, pro- US-
government, it will be pro Pakistan
and our brilliant right-wing analysts,
they don't understand that. What can I
say?
Yubra Singh Sikh Shikhawad says Arctic
geopolitics rising. Where does India
stand? I'm not sure India stands
anywhere in the Arctic geopolitics right
now. Uh we do have two or three research
stations in the Arctic which is a good
thing. Which is a good thing. So we have
a to hold there. Uh I think India should
invest in ice breakers and India should
should expand its footprint in the
Arctic. Um why am I talking about
Antarctica now? India has a footprint in
the Antarctica region. Well, see when it
comes to Arctic geopolitics, China is a
near Arctic country. They they have a
way to get to reach the Arctic. Russia
is an Arctic country. So is Canada. So
is the US because Alaska and so is
Denmark because of Greenland. But India
is nowhere near the Arctic. So if India
wants to become involved in Arctic
geopolitics, we have to do it by
partnering with Russia. Not with the US,
Canada or Denmark with Russia. So
another reason for us to partner with
Russia. But India doesn't stand too
much. I mean really anywhere in Arctic
geopolitics right now. See because of
global warming the the northern trade,
the sea route will open up and there's a
lot of resources there,
oil, gas, whatnot, fisheries, much more.
Okay, Girish Rati says, "After the SEO
summit, Mr. Putin and Mr. Modi met
secretly off record." No, it was not
secretly, it was very publicly, but it
was off record in a car for 45 minutes.
Avoiding Beijing's notice, what was what
was so sensitive perhaps linked to Japan
that needed secrecy.
See when you have a summit in China and
you have let's say 20 world leaders
let's say three world leaders then every
single thing will be recorded whether
you know it or not whichever you room
you go to let's say Mr. Putin and Mr.
Modi go to a meeting room somewhere and
nobody else is there. Even that is going
to be recorded because there's going to
be sensors everywhere. The Chinese will
have sensors all over the place. They
want to know every single word that's
being spoken.
So when Mr. Modi, Mr. Putin want to have
a face-to-face conversation about
whatever the best solution is to go to
Mr. Putin's car which is entirely under
in under in the Russia's control and go
on a 45minut ride and then discuss
whatever you want to discuss. Even there
the Chinese will try to somehow eaves
drop but it may not be possible because
the Russians will have taken all the
possible counter measures. So what was
so sensitive? Well only Mr. Putin and
Mr. Modi know what was I don't know if
it's linked to Japan. I don't think it I
I doubt if it's linked to Japan. I think
it's more about India Russia relations
and maybe about China as well. Maybe
there was a discussion about about
what's the deal with China. Are we going
to make some progress? India, China.
What can Russia do about this? How is it
really how does it really stand between
Russia and China? How what was the deal
with Alaska? All of that stuff which we
don't want the Chinese to know about.
Right? So Mr. Modi and Mr. Putin have
their own onetoone relationship or
long-standing relationship. They don't
need the Chinese listening to that to
whatever they talk about. So it's good
that they had a long discussion and now
we look forward to Mr. Putin visiting
visiting India and having further
discussions.
Sedharma says isn't it time to move
beyond the debunked ideas of P and Oak
and Pravin Muan? This is not geopolitics
anyway. Uh how long will India hold on
to such stories instead of embracing
facts and looking moving forward with
progress? Pnok ah P and Oak I don't
know. I mean I've seen some of his uh
publications and definitely complete I
mean completely debunkable stuff. Pravin
moan look Pravin Moan is doing great
work. You may you may say perhaps that
some of the things he says you don't
agree with but some of the stuff some of
the the the the videos he makes are
really interesting.
So you cannot because one or two of the
ideas may not be entirely something you
agree with. Doesn't mean that everything
he does is bad. I actually have a high
regard for Pravin Mohan. Okay, I do. So
let's not put P and Oak and Pravin Mohan
in the same category. Pravin Moan I
think is doing great work overall. PN my
god I I don't want to comment about PN
but anyway let's discuss geopolitics
today. Yes. Um, the King Charles says,
"I'm sorry for all, but how can I save
my empire?" Well, ask your daddy, Mr.
Trump, as to how you can save your
empire, King Charles. King Carlos, King
Carlos. Okay, we have reached 1 hour, 2
minutes. I'm going to end this in like 5
minutes. Okay, so two more questions.
Jen says, can we not develop our jet
engines and other stuff by reverse
engineering existing stuff? You know,
even to reverse engineer something, you
need a very high level of tech
technological capability.
Let's say I give you this phone. Hm. A
phone. And I tell you to reverse
engineer it. Okay. Here is the phone.
Here it is. Take it. Reverse engineer
it. What will you do? Will you be able
to reverse engineer it? You need a
tremendous
level of technological knowhow to
reverse engineer even a phone. To
reverse engineer this microphone, to
reverse engineer anything, you need a
certain amount of technological knowhow.
Okay, even if you have the complete
blueprint of a jet engine, but if you
don't have the methological knowhow,
then what will you do about it? If you
don't have the capability, capacity to
to manufacture certain ceramics, what
will you do about it? You may be able to
develop a jet engine with the exact
specifications as per the blueprint, but
when you run it, the temperatures go so
high your turbine blades just melt away.
Then what will you do about it? Right?
It's not that easy that they're easy.
So that's the thing. It's it's pretty
difficult but we should keep on going at
it. Develop our own jet engines. We have
done some progress in it. Just keep keep
at it. Right.
Project smiling Buddha says why do our
business houses packs Americana unless
unlike Chinese? Why our business houses
packs Americana un unlike Chinese?
I'm not sure what you're asking. is our
you saying that our business houses are
pro America and like the Chinese it's
because India is a deeply mentally
colonized country and because we are a
deeply angopilic country and all our men
so many of so many Indians have family
in the west so we are kind of invested
in the west and we are very comfortable
with the west so that's why we are
different from the Chinese the Chinese
are very proud of being non-western we
are like yes sir we are western that
sort of thing mahar says is Ibrahimore a
Panaffrican leader. No, he's not a
Panaffrican leader thus far. Um, he is
the leader of what? Burkasu is it? Or
Nijair? Nger. Is it Nijair? Uh, but
look, one second. I
[Music]
he is the Burkina Faso inim president.
Yes. Is he a Panaffrican leader? He
could be one. He's a young man and uh he
has devasalized his country. Of course,
when you def devasalize your country,
you have to align with with some powers
and that has to be done. So yeah, but
it's too early to say if he is a
pan-African leader for that he will have
to achieve much more. But yeah, he has
done a a commendable job in devasalizing
his country and and uh and uh putting
his his country on the right path of
development and not being you know a
minion of the west. Arian Kapoor says
what's the best reply to the US and
Donald Trump and his minions? The best
reply is keep quiet and do your do your
work. Ignore them. The best reply is to
ignore them. They want India to respond
emotionally. They want our leaders, our
politicians to start speaking in the
same kind of language they are speaking.
Their language is crass. The language
Navaro uses and Trump uses is the kind
of language you will hear on the
streets. Actually, the kind of language
Trump uses at times, it's it's street
language. And Navaro is is a crass kind
of person. a guy who was in jail a year
ago. So they want India to respond in
that kind of language so that they can
tar India with with with a certain kind
of brush, right? The best reply is to
ignore them, not pick up the phone,
ignore them, do our work and go and take
our business wherever it is welcome.
That's the best reply to the US. And um
the long-term best reply is success. We
have to succeed. We have to become a
bigger and bigger larger and larger
economy and a more powerful nation.
That's the best reply.
The best reply is not a verbal reply.
It's never a verbal reply. When a bully
is bullying you, ignore the bully and do
your work and then become bigger than
the bully. Then we'll talk a
Okay. All right folks, I think we are
done for the day. We have crossed 1 hour
6 minutes. Uh okay. I'm going to end it.
Hoya. Thank you so much for all the
questions. I apologize for the couple of
interruptions we had. I don't know what
the hell on earth all of that is. But uh
one last question. Okay, one last
question. Will this regime change tactic
by the US work? Time will tell. They
will try their best and they are really
good at this. The Americans do want a
regime change in India. All of us need
to be aware of this. Okay. The Americans
are very serious about a regime change
in India. So it's going to be very
dangerous the the coming days. All
right. Thank you. Thank you everybody.
Thank you so much once again. I
apologize for the interruptions but I
hope it was I hope it was valuable and I
look forward to seeing you in the next
live stream. Thank you so much
everybody. I really appreciate you all
and I look forward to seeing you in the
next one. Take care. Keep asking
questions. Keep learning. Keep raising
your standards. I'll see you soon.